Hello and welcome back to another video
with It's Dr. Dan and today we're going
to be learning about Vesper theory. So
this is where we're going to be taking
our Lewis structures. So if you saw my
previous video on Lewis structures,
we're going to be taking that and
bringing it into the 3D world. Being
that these different molecules that
we're seeing, they're not just something
that we write on paper. They they exist
in our everyday life. And being that we
ourselves live in a three-dimensional
world, so do they. Um, so when we are
looking at this, what is vesper? So if
you're taking a chemistry class, you
might have heard this concept. And this
is about valance shell electron pair
repulsion theory or vesper for short.
And why is it that we care about it?
Well, the whole idea is to try to figure
out what is the lowest energy
configuration for a molecule. Meaning,
when is it relaxed? So, for example,
like whenever you're at home, when are
you the most relaxed? Is it when you're
playing games, reading a book, or doing,
you know, whatever you you enjoy? Well,
molecules are the same way. They like to
have a point where they can be relaxed.
So, what we're actually going to be
trying to see is we're going to be
looking at different electron groups.
And what I mean by electron groups is
it's everything that is attached to the
central atom. So, whatever is in the
middle, whatever can make the most
friends um in that le structure, they're
going to be bound to all these atoms.
But what's going to be happening is the
atoms connected around the central the
central point are going to be repelling
each other like a magnet or like in this
gif that I found here, right? So they're
all going to be pushing each other away.
Now when they are doing that, they're
trying to spread as far apart as
possible but still be bound. So let's
first just start by practicing counting
electron groups. So, I'm going to draw a
couple Lewis structures and we're going
to be counting the number of groups.
Now, keep in mind groups can either be
um they can they can be lone pairs,
bonds, anything around it is considered
a group. So, when I write that down,
we're going to be counting lone pairs
and bonded electrons.
All right? So when we have those, so
let's say if I take our first one, let's
do what we're breathing out
all the time. So CO2. So if I have this
particular molecule, how many electron
groups do I have? Well, we are going to
first see that we have our central atom,
which is carbon. And we're going to be
counting how many things are connected
to it. So what we have is we have one
oxygen on the right hand side and then
we also have one oxygen
on the left hand side. So when we see
that we have one two electron groups on
this. So this one has two electron
groups.
Now if we look at a different molecule
let's say if I pick ammonia. So, if
you've ever uh maybe cleaned, you might
have used ammonia before. So, if I want
to draw this structure, we'd have
nitrogen as our central atom. And then
we want to count how many different
groups are there around this. So, some
of them could be if we have uh the
hydrogens each one of these is a is a
group. So we have one, two,
three different different electron
groups. But you can't forget we also
have to count the lone pairs cuz they
are also their own unique group. So when
we look at this, we have 1 2 3 four
groups all around that structure. If I
were to draw one more, well let's do
formaldahhide. So I have CO with a
double bond with two H's. We can once
again try to highlight all of our
different groups. So I have one for
oxygen and then I have one of the
hydrogens's on the left and then one on
the right. So how many electron groups
do I have? Well, this is going to be a
total of three electron groups. We just
fill those out. So three, four, and two
for all these different structures.
And that's what we're looking for is how
many electron groups. So now why how
should we think about that? So when it
comes to the different groups, what we
are trying to do is think of them as
bulky balloons. So meaning if you
imagine having balloons in your hand,
everybody's played with balloons at some
point and you were to hold them. Well,
if they if you were to tie the two at
the end at their at the bottom at the
knot, well, what would happen? Well,
they would bounce off each other and
they would repel each other. So, and
this is how we're going to be
determining the different geometries
behind them. So, if you think about a
circle um which is a complete perfect
shape. So, a circle if I were to kind of
draw that what is the angle for how many
degrees are in a circle? Wow. And that
did not draw well. So, if I have a
circle, how many degrees are there
around it? Well, there are 360
degrees. So, that is that perfect shape.
So, when we're adding groups, what we're
doing is taking that 360 and simply
dividing it by the number of by the
number of groups to kind of figure out
the general angle behind it. Um, now
that's more it represents more of a
two-dimensional space though. It's once
you start getting past four, five, six
groups, it starts getting a little bit
more intricate, a little bit more
unique, trying to purely push them
apart. So, if I have something that is
two groups, well, what's the farthest
they can be from each other? Well, think
of it as you inter if me and you are
interacting with each other. If we're
talking to each other right now in
person, we're going to be face to face
from each other. We're going to be 180°
apart. So, what that's going to be is if
I have my central atom right here in the
middle, well, and I have that as a
little knot that's being tied. If I have
two balloons, the blue and the red on
both sides, this is a linear geometry.
So, face to face. Now, that angle would
be 180°. Now, if we change that picture
to, let's say, three electron groups,
well, what's the the most that they can
be apart? So if I hold three balloons
that are all um far apart from each
other, um we can do that as well. So if
I have my three balloons and I want to
show all three of those, well we can see
that we have 1 2 3 a triangle would be
that perfect shape showing that 120° or
that tragonal planer is what this shape
is called. We can do four groups. So if
you think of tetra as four. So in this
one it's more drawn similar to like a
pyramid. So if we kind of think about
the connecting all these different
balloons via their corners, we can see
that oh well this is actually looking
like geometric shapes and how they're
all put together. So this one's
tetrahedral which has an angle of
109.5°.
Now, if you didn't notice, there's some
weird symbols that are being shown here.
So, what do all these represent? So, we
have this bold line. This is a wedge.
This is telling you that this balloon or
this atom is coming out at you. So, out
out of the screen and towards you. Where
I have these dashes,
they're going behind your monitor or
behind your phone right now. So that's
going away from you. So that's what
these are showing. When we just have a
regular line, this is representing that
it's being drawn in the plane. So if
you're like holding your device right
now, for example, it's in line with that
device. So it's in line with your screen
or whatever it is that you are actually
looking at. So we're drawing it in a
threedimensional
perspective.
So
now all these are all referring to just
electron groups or just atoms being
bound. What about lone pairs? What did
they do? Well, the thing is the thing
about lone pairs is that they are
extremely repulsive, meaning it's a
concentrated area of electrons. So
they're going to want to push everything
away from it. However, they're still
attached. We still interact with them.
We still have them around. But they're
like the friend that yes, you want to be
friends with them, but h you can only
handle them in small doses. So, you
know, you'll talk to them for maybe an
hour and then you'll step to step to the
other side of the room. That's kind of
what's happening here. So, they're a
little repulsive. So, what happens is
that these can change the geometry. So,
if we have our original tetrahedral
geometry on the left here, well, if I
decide to pop one of those balloons,
well, what's going to happen is you're
going to hear that loud bang and
everything's going to shutter away from
it. So, if we pop one of them and we
have our two lone pairs drawn here,
they're going to be pushing the other
elect all the different atoms away from
it. So it's going to be pushing them
downwards making constricting the angle.
So the 109.5 for tetrahedral is going to
become less than that and they're going
to all the the different atoms are going
to push together. So that'll be trigonal
pyramidal. Now when we add more lone
pairs or even more repulsive they're
going to push even farther away from
everything else. So that's going to
become bent. Now is this something that
you have to memorize every single one of
these? I hope not. I mean, if you're in
general chemistry for as a chemistry
major, you will have to memorize them.
But in introductory chem and high
school, a lot of times your your
professors, your teachers will give you
a reference sheet to be able to do to
actually be able to memorize or at least
be able to use this on homework. Maybe
for a while they'll eventually wean you
off of it. So for us, uh, we will have
this for at least for a while. Um, so
how does this work? So when we read
these charts, it looks a little scary at
first, but it's going through all the
different geometries that we just talked
about. So we went through the first four
here. So if I kind of just highlight
these and just make this a little
thicker just to show. So if we went
through the first four. So what this
refers to is steric number, which is the
same thing as saying electron group.
And let's do that in not as thick a
letter so that's readable. So these are
electron
groups and that is your steric number.
So that would be your first thing you're
going to be counting is how many
electron groups there are. You need to
draw the le structure behind these cuz
you need to know how many lone pairs
there are on the central atom. So this
is all referring to the geometry around
the central atom. Okay. So we need to
draw our le structure
and then we are trying to look at the
central atom geometry
when we are looking at these. So let's
practice using this chart. So if I take
a few different structures. So let's say
if I go back to some of the ones I drew
earlier first. So if I had CO2.
So what we are doing here is once again
we are counting
how many different groups there are. And
whether or not you remember from earlier
right there are two groups on each side
of this molecule. So
when we see this, right, we have one,
two. So what we're going to be then
doing is going to our chart here. Let's
just clean this up a little bit. We're
going to be referring to this as our
central atom. So the letter E that are
here are your central atom. So you can
see there's E at the beginning of like
all these different species here. That's
your central. The X's are what's bound
to that central atom. So on this last
one, we had we had two electron groups
on this. So what we're going to do is
we're going to go to the two. There was
no lone pairs around CO2. So what that
tells you is that the geometry is
linear, right? So we see no lone pairs,
only those different groups. So this is
our linear
geometry for this species.
So that's what that tells you. So that
tells you that they're 180° apart. This
is linear. So let's try let's try a
different one. What if I had
CO with two H's on it? Well, once again,
we're looking at carbon as our central
atom.
And then we're going to be counting the
different groups. So we have one, I
don't know why that kind of went away.
one, two, and three here on each side.
We're then going to be looking at the
different groups. So, we have three. We
had zero lone pairs on this structure.
So, what that's going to be, it's going
to be trigonal planer is going to be our
geometry. So, we can redraw this
molecule in that orientation. So when we
do that,
we're going to draw this as trigonal
planer.
So we have that C double bonded O. We
would show the triangular shape behind
it. So this illustrates that there's
120° between each of these different
groups. Let's try a different one. What
if I have water? So water, which is one
of the ones that we did in our previous
videos quite a bit, is water is a
central atom.
It's connected to hydrogens's on both
sides.
So how many electron groups does this
one have? Well, once again, we're going
to count. So we have one, two atoms on
both sides. I'm not sure why that's
disappearing.
So we'll just write it. So we have one
two groups on each side. We have a lone
pair which is three and then four on all
sides. So however there might be four
electron groups but how many lone pairs
are there? So we have four electron
groups
and two lone pairs. So when we are doing
this we're going to go back up to our
chart. We're going to then be reading
across. we'll see we have four and we
also are referring to having two loan
pairs. So we're going to go to our two
lone pairs here. So we're going to come
down and across and we can see that
we're going to have a bent geometry for
water. So if we draw that now we can
redraw our structure of water. We have
our two lone pairs on top like little
ears. And then each of the hydrogens are
pointing downwards. So now we can show
that we have less than
109.5°
for water. And that's how we would draw
that. Let's try a couple others. Let's
try two more. Let's say if we did CH4,
how would we draw that one? So with
carbon, there's going to be four groups
and there's no lone pairs around the
structure. So we can draw it. We can see
that there's a hydrogen on all sides
just like this. So what geometry would
have four different groups? Well, we can
see that four groups is right on the
left hand side here and there's no lone
pairs on it. So this is going to be
tetrahedral is going to be our geometry.
So why don't we redraw that as
tetrahedral.
So this be c h
we'll draw a wedge
and then a dash to show we have a
tetrahedral
geometry.
Okay let's label these other ones real
quick. So this was bent. This was
tragonal planer
and this was uh linear up there. So now
the last one let's do another one. Let's
say if I gave
something a little different.
Let's do a let's do a slightly harder
one. So, SF6
is an octet rule violator,
which we'll talk about in future videos,
meaning that it can expand past a normal
octet. So, it can make more than it can
make more than the two bonds that sulfur
normally can do. So, if sulfur is a
central atom and I can tell you that all
right, it's going to bond to all the
florines. So, it's going to look like
with all the florines on all sides. So
what geometry would six groups be on all
sides? So we have 1 2 3 4 5 six. How do
we do that? Well,
we would see that we have six. There was
no lone pairs on it. This one's going to
be ocahedral.
So if we were going to draw this one,
well, we have it pretty close. We would
draw sulfur. two two of them are
pointing up and down in the plane. The
rest of them are pointing two of them
are pointing out
just like so with wedges
and then we would draw two of them going
away from us as dashes. So this is
octahhedral.
How does these angles work? So with
these it's kind of interesting. So, we
have 90° on the sides and then down like
the middle, it's like 180 down the
middle or 90° on the on all parts for
the most part. So, between what you want
to go between. So, it's it's a pretty
different geometry. So, uh when you're
going through this, this is the basics
of how to uh draw use the Vesper chart
when you're going through this. And I
hope this video helped you to be able to
figure out figure out the geometries and
to build off of the different Lewis
structures. So this is Dr. Dan and
please consider hitting that like and
subscribe button for future videos and
I'll see you all later. Bye.
[Music]